Well, as many of you know,
حسناً، كما يعلم الكثير منكم،
the results of the recent election were as follows:
فإن نتيجة الإنتخابات الأخيرة كانت كالتالي:
Hillary Clinton, the Democratic candidate
(هيلاري كلينتون)، المرشحة الديمقراطية
won a landslide victory
حققت فوزاً ساحقاً
with 52 percent of the overall vote.
بنسبة 52 في المئة من إجمالي التصويت.
Jill Stein, the Green candidate,
(جيل ستاين)، مرشحة الحزب الأخضر،
came a distant second, with 19 percent.
أتت في المركز الثاني، بنسبة 19 في المئة.
Donald J. Trump, the Republic candidate,
(دونالد ترامب)، المرشح الجمهوري،
was hot on her heels with 14 percent,
يتبعها عن كثب بنسبة 14 في المئة،
and the remainder of the vote were shared between abstainers
وباقي التصويت تم تقاسمه بين الممتنعين عن التصويت
and Gary Johnson, the Libertarian candidate.
و(جاري جونسون)، المرشح الليبرالي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, what parallel universe do you suppose I live in?
الآن، ما هو العالم المواز الذي تظنون أنني أعيش فيه؟
Well, I don't live in a parallel universe.
حسناً، أنا لا أعيش في عالم مواز.
I live in the world, and that is how the world voted.
أنا أعيش في هذا العالم، وهكذا صوت العالم.
So let me take you back and explain what I mean by that.
لذا دعوني أرجع بكم للوراء وأشرح لكم ما أقصده بهذا.
In June this year,
في يونيو من هذا العام،
I launched something called the Global Vote.
أطلقت ما يُعرف باسم التصويت العالمي.
And the Global Vote does exactly what it says on the tin.
والتصويت العالمي يقوم بالضبط بما يعنيه اسمه.
For the first time in history,
للمرة الأولى في التاريخ،
it lets anybody, anywhere in the world,
يُسمح لأي شخص، في أي مكان بالعالم،
vote in the elections of other people's countries.
بالتصويت في انتخابات دول أخرى.
Now, why would you do that?
الآن، لم قد تفعل ذلك؟
What's the point?
ما هو الهدف وراء ذلك؟
Well, let me show you what it looks like.
حسناً، دعوني أريكم كيف يبدو الأمر.
You go to a website,
تدخل إلى موقع إلكتروني،
rather a beautiful website,
موقع جميل في الواقع،
and then you select an election.
ثم تختار تصويتاً.
Here's a bunch that we've already covered.
إليكم مجموعة قمنا بتغطيتها بالفعل.
We do about one a month, or thereabouts.
نجري حوالي واحد في الشهر، أو ما يقرب من ذلك.
So you can see Bulgaria, the United States of America,
يمكنكم أن تروا بلغاريا، والولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
Secretary-General of the United Nations,
والأمين العام للأمم المتحدة،
the Brexit referendum at the end there.
الاستفتاء على خروج المملكة المتحدة من الاتحاد الأوروبي هنا في النهاية.
You select the election that you're interested in,
تقوم باختيار التصويت الذي تهتم به،
and you pick the candidates.
ومن ثم تختار المرشحين.
These are the candidates from the recent presidential election
هؤلاء هم المرشحون في الانتخابات الرئاسية الأخيرة
in the tiny island nation of São Tomé and Príncipe,
في دولة جزيرتي (ساو تومي) و(برينسيبي) الصغيرة جداً،
199,000 inhabitants,
199,000 مواطن،
off the coast of West Africa.
قبالة سواحل غرب أفريقيا.
And then you can look at the brief summary of each of those candidates
وتستطيع بعد ذلك أن تقرأ الملخص الموجز لكل مرشح منهم
which I dearly hope is very neutral,
والذي أطمح بشدة أن يكون حياديًا جداً،
very informative and very succinct.
حافلًا جداً بالمعلومات ومقتضب جداً.
And when you've found the one you like, you vote.
وعندما تجد من تفضله، تقوم حينها بالتصويت.
These were the candidates
هؤلاء كانوا المرشحين
in the recent Icelandic presidential election,
في الانتخابات الرئاسية الأيسلندية الأخيرة،
and that's the way it goes.
وهكذا تسير الأمور.
So why on earth would you want to vote in another country's election?
إذاً لم قد ترغب في التصويت في انتخابات دولة أخرى؟
Well, the reason that you wouldn't want to do it,
حسناً، إن السبب الذي يجعلك لا ترغب في فعل ذلك،
let me reassure you,
دعني أؤكد لك،
is in order to interfere in the democratic processes of another country.
هو رغبتك في ألا تتدخل في العملية الديموقراطية لدولة أخرى.
That's not the purpose at all.
ليس هذا الهدف على الإطلاق.
In fact, you can't,
في الواقع، أنت لا تستطيع،
because usually what I do is I release the results
لأن ما أفعله عادة هو أنني أطلق النتائج
after the electorate in each individual country has already voted,
بعدما يقوم الناخبين في كل دولة على حده بالتصويت بالفعل،
so there's no way that we could interfere in that process.
بحيث لا يكون هناك مجالاً لأن نتدخل في تلك العملية.
But more importantly,
ولكن الشيء الأكثر أهمية،
I'm not particularly interested
أنا لست مهتماً بالتحديد
in the domestic issues of individual countries.
بالقضايا المحلية لكل دولة على حدة.
That's not what we're voting on.
ليس هذا ما نصوت عليه.
So what Donald J. Trump or Hillary Clinton proposed to do for the Americans
إذاً فما يقترح فعله كلٌّ من (دونالد ترامب) أو (هيلاري كلينتون) للأمريكيين
is frankly none of our business.
هو في الحقيقة ليس من شأننا على الإطلاق.
That's something that only the Americans can vote on.
هذا شيء من حق الأمريكيين فقط التصويت عليه.
No, in the global vote, you're only considering one aspect of it,
لكن في التصويت العالمي، أنت تأخذ في الاعتبار جانبًا واحدًا فقط من الأمر،
which is what are those leaders going to do for the rest of us?
وهو ماذا سيفعل هؤلاء القادة لنا نحن؟
And that's so very important because we live,
وهذا أمر هام جداً لأننا نعيش،
as no doubt you're sick of hearing people tell you,
وبالطبع أنتم سئمتم من سماع هذا،
in a globalized, hyperconnected, massively interdependent world
في عالم يتسم بالعولمة، شديد الاتصال، ومترابط بشكل كبير
where the political decisions of people in other countries
حيث القرارات السياسية للأشخاص في الدول الأخرى
can and will have an impact on our lives
تستطيع أن، وستتمكن من التأثير في حياتنا
no matter who we are, no matter where we live.
بغض النظر عن من نكون، وبغض النظر عن أين نعيش.
Like the wings of the butterfly
مثل أجنحة الفراشة
beating on one side of the Pacific
تضرب على جانب من المحيط الهادئ
that can apparently create a hurricane on the other side,
مما قد يخلق إعصاراً في الجانب الآخر،
so it is with the world that we live in today
هكذا هو الأمر في العالم الذي نحيا فيه اليوم
and the world of politics.
وعالم السياسة.
There is no longer a dividing line between domestic and international affairs.
لم يعد هناك خط فاصل بين الشؤون المحلية والدولية.
Any country, no matter how small,
فأية دولة، مهما كانت صغيرة،
even if it's São Tomé and Príncipe,
حتى إن كانت (ساو تومي) و(برينسيبي)،
could produce the next Nelson Mandela
قد تنجب (نيلسون مانديلا) جديداً
or the next Stalin.
أو (ستالين) آخر.
They could pollute the atmosphere and the oceans, which belong to all of us,
قد يلوثوا الغلاف الجوي والمحيطات، التي تنتمي لنا جميعاً،
or they could be responsible and they could help all of us.
أو قد يكونوا على قدر من المسؤولية ويتمكنوا من مساعدتنا جميعاً.
And yet, the system is so strange
ولكن، النظام غريب جداً
because the system hasn't caught up with this globalized reality.
لأنه لم يواكب هذا الواقع المتسم بالعولمة.
Only a small number of people are allowed to vote for those leaders,
عدد قليل فقط من الأشخاص هم المسموح لهم بالتصويت لهؤلاء القادة،
even though their impact is gigantic
بالرغم من أن تأثيرهم هائل
and almost universal.
ويكاد يكون عالمياً.
What number was it?
كم بلغ العدد؟
140 million Americans voted
140 مليون أمريكي قام بالتصويت
for the next president of the United States,
للرئيس المقبل للولايات المتحدة.
and yet, as all of us knows, in a few weeks time,
وكما نعلم جميعاً، ففي غضون أسابيع قليلة،
somebody is going to hand over the nuclear launch codes
سيقوم أحدهم بتسليم شفرات إطلاق السلاح النووي
to Donald J. Trump.
إلى (دونالد ترامب).
Now, if that isn't having a potential impact on all of us,
الآن، إذا لم يكن لهذا الأمر أثر محتمل علينا جميعاً،
I don't know what is.
فأنا لا أعلم ما الذي يمكنه أن يكون ذا أثر إذاً.
a small number of millions of British people voted on that,
قام عدد قليل من ملايين البريطانيين بالتصويت على ذلك الأمر،
but the outcome of the vote, whichever way it went,
ولكن أياً ما كان ناتج هذا التصويت،
would have had a significant impact
سيكون له تأثير واضح
on the lives of tens, hundreds of millions of people around the world.
على حياة العشرات، ومئات الملايين من الأشخاص حول العالم.
And yet, only a tiny number could vote.
ومع ذلك، فإن عددًا قليلًا جداً هو من يمكنه التصويت.
What kind of democracy is that?
أي ديمقراطية هذه؟
Huge decisions that affect all of us
قرارات عظيمة تؤثر بنا جميعاً
being decided by relatively very small numbers of people.
تؤخذ بواسطة عدد قليل جداً نسبياً من الأشخاص.
And I don't know about you,
وأنا لا أعلم رأيكم في الأمر،
but I don't think that sounds very democratic.
ولكن أنا لا أعتقد أن هذا يبدو ديمقراطياً.
So I'm trying to clear it up.
لذا أحاول أن أوضح الأمر.
But as I say,
ولكن كما أقول،
we don't ask about domestic questions.
نحن لا نسأل عما يتعلق بالقضايا المحلية.
In fact, I only ever ask two questions of all of the candidates.
في الواقع، أنا أسأل سؤالين فقط لجميع المرشحين.
I send them the same two questions every single time.
وأرسل لهم نفس السؤالين في كل مرة.
I say, one,
أقول في السؤال الأول،
if you get elected, what are you going to do for the rest of us,
إذا تم انتخابك، ما الذي ستفعله لبقيتنا؟
for the remainder of the seven billion who live on this planet?
للسبعة مليار شخص الباقين الذين يعيشون على هذا الكوكب؟
Second question:
السؤال الثاني:
What is your vision for your country's future in the world?
ما هي رؤيتك لمستقبل بلادك في العالم؟
What role do you see it playing?
ما رؤيتك للدور الذي ستلعبه؟
Every candidate, I send them those questions.
أُرسل تلك الأسئلة لكل مرشح،
They don't all answer. Don't get me wrong.
لا يجيب الجميع. لا تسيئوا فهمي.
I reckon if you're standing
أظن أنك إذا كنت تستعد
to become the next president of the United States,
لتصبح الرئيس القادم للولايات المتحدة،
you're probably pretty tied up most of the time,
ستكون مكتوف اليدين معظم الوقت،
so I'm not altogether surprised that they don't all answer, but many do.
لذا أنا لست متفاجئاً بأنني لم أتلق رداً من الجميع، ولكن الكثير يفعلون.
More every time.
وفي كل مرة يزداد العدد.
And some of them do much more than answer.
وبعضهم يقوم بما هو أكثر من مجرد رد.
Some of them answer in the most enthusiastic and most exciting way
بعضهم يجيبون بأكثر الطرق الحماسية والمثيرة
you could imagine.
التي يمكنكم تخيلها.
I just want to say a word here for Saviour Chishimba,
أريد أن أوجه كلمة إلى (سافيور تشيشيمبا)،
who was one of the candidates
الذي كان واحداً من المرشحين
in the recent Zambian presidential election.
في الانتخابات الرئاسية الأخيرة بزامبيا.
His answers to those two questions were basically an 18-page dissertation
كانت إجاباته على هذين السؤالين عبارة عن مقال من 18 صفحة
on his view of Zambia's potential role in the world
عن رؤيته لدور زامبيا المحتمل في العالم
and in the international community.
وفي المجتمع الدولي.
I posted it on the website so anybody could read it.
قمت بنشرها على الموقع حتى يتمكن الجميع من قراءتها.
Now, Saviour won the global vote,
الآن، فاز (سافيور) بالتصويت العالمي،
but he didn't win the Zambian election.
ولكنه لم يفز بانتخابات زامبيا.
So I found myself wondering,
لذا وجدتني أتساءل،
what am I going to do with this extraordinary group of people?
ماذا سأفعل مع هذه المجموعة الاستثنائية من الأشخاص؟
I've got some wonderful people here who won the global vote.
لدي أشخاص رائعون هنا فازوا بنتيجة التصويت العالمي.
We always get it wrong, by the way.
دائماً نفهم الأمر بطريقة خاطئة، بالمناسبة.
The one that we elect
فالشخص الذي ننتخبه
is never the person who's elected by the domestic electorate.
ليس هو الشخص الذي تم انتخابه من قبل الناخبين المحليين.
That may be partly because we always seem to go for the woman.
قد يرجع ذلك جزئياً إلى ميلنا نحو المرأة.
But I think it may also be a sign
ولكن أعتقد أيضاً أنها قد تكون إشارة
that the domestic electorate is still thinking very nationally.
إلى أن الناخبين المحليين ما زالوا يفكرون بطريقة وطنية للغاية.
They're still thinking very inwardly.
ما زالوا يفكرون في الداخل بشكل كبير.
They're still asking themselves: What's in it for me? ...
وما زالوا يسألون أنفسهم: ما العائد عليَ؟
instead of what they should be asking today,
عوضاً عما يجب أن يسألوه اليوم،
which is, what's in it for we?
وهو، ما العائد علينا؟
But there you go.
لكن ها نحن ذا.
So suggestions, please, not right now,
لذا رجاء قدموا اقتراحاتكم، ليس الآن،
but send me an email if you've got an idea
ولكن بالبريد الإلكتروني، إذا كان لديكم فكرة
about what we can do with this amazing team of glorious losers.
عن ما يمكن أن نفعله مع هذا الفريق الهائل من الخاسرين الرائعين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We've got Saviour Chishimba, who I mentioned before.
لدينا (سافيور تشيشيمبا)، الذي ذكرته من قبل.
We've got Halla Tómasdóttir,
ولدينا (هلا توماسدوتر)،
who was the runner up in the Icelandic presidential election.
التي كانت في المركز الثاني في الانتخابات الرئاسية بآيسلندا.
Many of you may have seen her amazing talk at TEDWomen
قد يكون الكثير منكم شاهدوا حديثها الرائع في TEDWomen
just a few weeks ago
قبل بضعة أسابيع
where she spoke about the need for more women to get into politics.
حيث تحدثت عن الحاجة لدخول نساء أكثر في مجال السياسة.
We've got Maria das Neves from São Tomé and Príncipe.
لدينا أيضاً (ماريا داس نيفز) من (ساو تومي) و(برينسيبي).
We've got Hillary Clinton.
ولدينا (هيلاري كلينتون).
I don't know if she's available.
لا أعلم إن كانت متاحة.
We've got Jill Stein.
لدينا (جيل ستاين).
And we covered also the election
وقد قمنا أيضاً بتغطية الانتخابات
for the next Secretary-General of the United Nations.
الخاصة بالأمين العام للأمم المتحدة القادم.
We've got the ex-prime minister of New Zealand,
لدينا رئيس الوزراء السابق لنيوزيلندا،
who would be a wonderful member of the team.
والذي سيكون عضوًا هائلًا في الفريق.
So I think maybe those people,
لذا أعتقد أن هؤلاء الأشخاص،
the glorious loser's club, could travel around the world
نادي الخاسرون الرائعون، قد يجوبوا العالم
wherever there's an election
أينما تكون هناك انتخابات
and remind people of the necessity in our modern age
ويذكروا الناس في عصرنا الحديث بأهمية
of thinking a little bit outwards
التفكير للخارج قليلاً
and thinking of the international consequences.
والتفكير في العواقب الدولية.
So what comes next for the global vote?
إذاً ما هي الخطوة التالية للتصويت العالمي؟
Well, obviously,
حسناً، من الواضح،
the Donald and Hillary show is a bit of a difficult one to follow,
أن عرض (دونالد) و(هيلاري) من الصعب تعقبه،
but there are some other really important elections coming up.
ولكن هناك انتخابات أخرى قادمة هامة جداً.
In fact, they seem to be multiplying.
في الحقيقة، يبدو أنهم يتضاعفون.
There's something going on, I'm sure you've noticed, in the world.
هناك شيء ما يجري في العالم، وأنا واثق أنكم قد لاحظتموه.
And the next row of elections are all critically important.
والجولة القادمة من الانتخابات ستكون جميعها بالغة الأهمية.
In just a few day's time
فبعد بضعة أيام
we've got the rerun of the Austrian presidential election,
ستجرى إعادة الانتخابات الرئاسية النمساوية،
with the prospect of Norbert Hofer
مع وجود احتمال ل(نوربرت هوفر)
becoming what is commonly described
بأن يصبح ما يتم وصفه عادة
as the first far-right head of state in Europe since the Second World War.
كأول رئيس دولة يميني متطرف في أوروبا منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية.
Next year we've got Germany,
العام المقبل لدينا ألمانيا،
we've got France,
ولدينا فرنسا،
we've got presidential elections in Iran
وهناك انتخابات رئاسية في إيران
and a dozen others.
وعشرات أخرى.
It doesn't get less important.
لا يصبح الأمر أقل أهمية أبداً.
It gets more and more important.
بل يزداد أهمية أكثر وأكثر.
Clearly, the global vote is not a stand-alone project.
من الواضح، أن التصويت العالمي ليس مشروعًا قائمًا بذاته.
It's not just there on its own.
فهو ليس هناك بذاته.
It has some background.
فهناك خلفية وراءه.
It's part of a project which I launched back in 2014,
فهو جزء من مشروع أطلقته عام 2014،
which I call the Good Country.
وأسميته الدولة الصالحة.
The idea of the Good Country is basically very simple.
إن الفكرة وراء الدولة الصالحة سهلة للغاية.
It's my simple diagnosis of what's wrong with the world
هي تشخيصي البسيط لما يدور في العالم
and how we can fix it.
وكيف يمكننا إصلاحه.
What's wrong with the world I've already hinted at.
قد ألمحت مسبقاً لما يحدث في العالم.
Basically, we face an enormous and growing number
نحن نواجه بشكل أساسي عدد ضخم ومتزايد
of gigantic, existential global challenges:
من التغيرات العالمية الوجودية الضخمة:
climate change, human rights abuses,
تغيرات المناخ، وانتهاكات حقوق الإنسان،
mass migration, terrorism, economic chaos, weapons proliferation.
والهجرة الجماعية، والإرهاب، والفوضى الاقتصادية، وانتشار الأسلحة.
All of these problems which threaten to wipe us out
كل هذه المشاكل التي تهدد بالقضاء علينا جميعاً
are by their very nature globalized problems.
هي بطبيعتها مشاكل تتسم بالعولمة.
No individual country has the capability of tackling them on its own.
لا تستطيع دولة التصدي لها بمفردها.
And so very obviously
ومن الواضح جداً
we have to cooperate and we have to collaborate as nations
أنه علينا أن نتعاون وأن نتحد كأمم
if we're going to solve these problems.
إذا كنا سنقوم بحل تلك المشكلات.
It's so obvious, and yet we don't.
هذا أمر واضح جداً، ولكننا لا نفعل ذلك.
We don't do it nearly often enough.
لا نفعل ذلك بما فيه الكفاية تقريباً.
Most of the time, countries still persist in behaving
فأغلب الوقت، مازالت الدول تصر على التصرف
as if they were warring, selfish tribes battling against each other,
كأنهم قبائل أنانية متناحرة تصارع بعضها البعض،
much as they have done since the nation-state was invented
كما فعلوا دائماً منذ نشأة الدول القومية
hundreds of years ago.
منذ مئات السنين.
And this has got to change.
وحان الوقت لتغيير هذا.
This is not a change in political systems or a change in ideology.
فهذا ليس تغييرًا في أنظمة سياسية أو تغييرًا في المذهب.
This is a change in culture.
هذا تغيير في الثقافة.
We, all of us, have to understand
يجب علينا جميعاً أن ندرك
that thinking inwards is not the solution to the world's problems.
أن التفكير في الشأن الداخلي ليس الحل لمشكلات العالم.
We have to learn how to cooperate and collaborate a great deal more
علينا أن نتعلم كيف نتعاون بشكل أكبر
and compete just a tiny bit less.
ونتنافس بشكل أقل قليلاً.
Otherwise things are going to carry on getting bad
ما عدا ذلك ستستمر الأمور في أخذ منحنى سيء
and they're going to get much worse, much sooner than we anticipate.
وستزداد سوءاً، أسرع مما نتوقع.
This change will only happen
سيحدث هذا التغيير فقط
if we ordinary people
إذا قمنا نحن كأشخاص عاديين
tell our politicians that things have changed.
بإخبار ساستنا بأن الأمور قد تغيرت.
We have to tell them that the culture has changed.
علينا إخبارهم بأن الثقافة تغيرت.
that they've got a new mandate.
علينا إخبارهم بأنه قد صار لديهم تكليف جديد.
The old mandate was very simple and very single:
كان التكليف القديم سهلًا جداً وأحادياً جداً
if you're in a position of power or authority,
إذا كنت في موقع قوة أو سلطة،
you're responsible for your own people and your own tiny slice of territory,
فأنت مسؤول عن شعبك فقط وعن قطعتك الضئيلة جداً من الإقليم،
and that's it.
وهذا كل ما في الأمر.
And if in order to do the best thing for your own people,
وإذا تطلب منك الأمر من أجل تحقيق الأفضل لشعبك،
you screw over everybody else on the planet, that's even better.
أن تخرب حياة أي شخص آخر على سطح الكوكب، فهذا حتى أفضل بكثير.
That's considered to be a bit macho.
يعد هذا فرضاً للهيمنة بعض الشيء.
Today, I think everybody in a position of power and responsibility
اليوم، أعتقد أن كل شخص في موقع قوة ومسئولية
has got a dual mandate,
لديه مهمة مزدوجة،
which says if you're in a position of power and responsibility,
والتي تقتضي أنك إذا كنت في موقع قوة ومسؤولية،
you're responsible for your own people
فأنت مسئول عن قومك
and for every single man, woman, child and animal on the planet.
وعن كل رجل، امرأة، طفل، وحيوان على سطح الكوكب.
You're responsible for your own slice of territory
أنت مسئول عن قطعتك من الإقليم الخاص بك
and for every single square mile of the earth's surface
وعن كل ميل مربع من سطح الأرض
and the atmosphere above it.
والغلاف الجوي المحيط به.
And if you don't like that responsibility, you should not be in power.
وإذا كنت لا تحب هذه المسؤولية، فلا يجب أن تكون في السلطة.
That for me is the rule of the modern age,
بالنسبة لي فتلك هي قاعدة العصر الحديث،
and that's the message that we've got to get across to our politicians,
وتلك هي الرسالة التي علينا توصيلها لساستنا،
and show them that that's the way things are done these days.
وأن نبين لهم أن الأمور تسير على هذا النحو هذه الآونة.
Otherwise, we're all screwed.
وإلا سنهلك جميعاً.
I don't have a problem, actually,
في الواقع أنا ليس لدي أية مشكلة،
with Donald Trump's credo of "America first."
مع عقيدة (دونالد ترامب) المتمثلة في "أمريكا أولاً".
It seems to me that that's a pretty banal statement
يبدو لي هذا بيانًا عاديًا
of what politicians have always done and probably should always do.
لما فعله السياسيون دائماً ومن المحتمل أن يستمروا دائماً بفعله.
Of course they're elected to represent the interests of their own people.
بالطبع هم منتخبون لتمثيل اهتمامات شعبهم.
But what I find so boring and so old-fashioned
ولكن ما أجده أمرًا مملًا جداً وقديمًا جداً
and so unimaginative about his take on that
وضيق الأفق جداً في اضطلاعه بهذا الأمر
is that America first means everyone else last,
هو أن "أمريكا أولاً" تعني أن الباقين في المرتبة الأخيرة،
that making America great again means making everybody else small again,
وأن جعل أمريكا عظيمة مرة أخرى يعني جعل الآخرين صغاراً مجدداًَ،
and it's just not true.
وهذا ليس صحيحاً بالمرة.
In my job as a policy advisor over the last 20 years or so,
في وظيفتي كمستشار سياسي لأكثر من 20 عاماً أو شيئاً كهذا،
I've seen so many hundreds of examples of policies
رأيت مئات الأمثلة على سياسات
that harmonize the international and the domestic needs,
تقوم بالتوفيق بين الاحتياجات الدولية والمحلية،
and they make better policy.
ويصنعون سياسة أفضل.
I'm not asking nations to be altruistic or self-sacrificing.
أنا لا أطالب الأمم بأن تؤثِر الآخرين أو تضحى بنفسها.
That would be ridiculous.
سيكون هذا سخيفاً.
No nation would ever do that.
لن تفعل أي أمة هذا الأمر.
I'm asking them to wake up and understand that we need a new form of governance,
أنا أطالبهم بأن ينتبهوا ويتفهموا أننا بحاجة إلى حوكمة جديدة،
which is possible
وهو أمر محتمل
and which harmonizes those two needs,
ويقوم بالتوفيق بين هذين الاحتياجين،
those good for our own people and those good for everybody else.
ما هو جيد لشعبنا وما هو جيد للجميع.
Since the US election and since Brexit
منذ انتخابات الولايات المتحدة، ومنذ استفتاء خروج بريطانيا
it's become more and more obvious to me
أصبح الأمر جلياً أكثر بالنسبة لي
that those old distinctions of left wing and right wing
أن حالات التمييز القديمة بين الجناح اليساري والجناح اليميني
no longer make sense.
لم تعد منطقية.
They really don't fit the pattern.
إنها لا تتناسب بحق مع النمط المُتبع.
What does seem to matter today
ما يبدو مهماً اليوم
is very simple,
بسيط جداً،
whether your view of the world is
ما إذا كانت نظرتك للعالم
that you take comfort from looking inwards and backwards,
أنك تجد الراحة في النظر للداخل وللوراء،
or whether, like me, you find hope in looking forwards and outwards.
أو إذا كنت مثلي، تجد الأمل في النظر للأمام وللخارج.
That's the new politics.
تلك هي السياسات الجديدة.
That's the new division that is splitting the world right down the middle.
تلك هي التفرقة الجديدة التي تقسم العالم من المنتصف.
Now, that may sound judgmental, but it's not meant to be.
الآن، قد يبدو هذا انتقادياً، ولكن هذا ليس مقصوداً.
I don't at all misunderstand
أنا لا أسيء الفهم مطلقاً
why so many people find their comfort in looking inwards and backwards.
عن سبب إيجاد الكثير من الأشخاص الراحة في النظر للداخل وللوراء.
When times are difficult, when you're short of money,
حين تشتد الأمور، حين ينقصك المال،
when you're feeling insecure and vulnerable,
وحين تشعر بعدم الأمان وبالضعف،
it's almost a natural human tendency to turn inwards,
فاللجوء للداخل هو تصرف بشري طبيعي،
to think of your own needs
أن تفكر في احتياجاتك الخاصة
and to discard everybody else's,
وأن تستبعد احتياجات الجميع،
and perhaps to start to imagine that the past was somehow better
وقد تبدأ أيضاً في التفكير في أن الوضع في الماضي كان أفضل إلى حد ما
than the present or the future could ever be.
أفضل حتى عما يمكن أن يكونه الحاضر أو المستقبل.
But I happen to believe that that's a dead end.
ولكني أعتقد أن هذا طريق مسدود.
History shows us that it's a dead end.
يوضح لنا التاريخ انه طريق مسدود.
When people turn inwards and turn backwards,
حين يلتفت الناس للداخل وللوراء،
human progress becomes reversed
ينعكس مسار التقدم الإنساني
and things get worse for everybody very quickly indeed.
وتزداد الأمور سوءاً على الجميع بسرعة كبيرة.
If you're like me
إذا كنت مثلي
and you believe in forwards and outwards,
وتؤمن بالنظر للأمام وللخارج،
and you believe that the best thing about humanity is its diversity,
وتؤمن بأن أفضل ما في البشرية هو تنوعها،
and the best thing about globalization
وأن أفضل ما في العولمة
is the way that it stirs up that diversity, that cultural mixture
هي طريقتها في تحريك ذلك التنوع، وهذا الخليط الحضاري
to make something more creative, more exciting, more productive
لصنع شيء أكثر إبداعاً، وأكثر إثارة، وأكثر إنتاجاً
than there's ever been before in human history,
من أي وقت مضى في تاريخ البشرية،
then, my friends, we've got a job on our hands,
إذاً أصدقائي، فنحن لدينا عمل لنقوم به،
because the inwards and backwards brigade
لأن فرقة الداخل والوراء
are uniting as never before,
تتحد كما لم تفعل من قبل،
and that creed of inwards and backwards,
وذلك المذهب القائم على النظر للداخل وللوراء،
that fear, that anxiety,
هذا الخوف، وهذا القلق،
playing on the simplest instincts,
واللعب على أبسط الغرائز،
is sweeping across the world.
يجتاح العالم.
Those of us who believe,
من يؤمن منا،
as I believe, in forwards and outwards,
كما أؤمن أنا، بالنظر للأمام وللخارج،
we have to get ourselves organized,
فإنه يجب علينا أن ننظم أنفسنا،
because time is running out very, very quickly.
لأن الوقت يمر سريعاً جداً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)